<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-02-20T15:38:43-05:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><entry><title type="html">Book Review: No Man’s Land by Mathews Vigna</title><link href="/2022/02/17/NoMansLand.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Book Review: No Man’s Land by Mathews Vigna" /><published>2022-02-17T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-02-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/2022/02/17/NoMansLand</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2022/02/17/NoMansLand.html">&lt;p&gt;I didn’t expect to like this book. Actually, I had to force myself to start reading it after renewing it from the library a week late. Once I got started, though, I couldn’t put it down. This review contains many spoilers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No Man’s Land tells the story of generations (?) of people struggling to transcend their circumstances. Davey, the 14-year-old protagonist, is rescued from a battlefield and raised in a violent pillaging cult. She is characterized from the beginning as being an outsider to the group who dares to question those around her. She cannot leave the group because she has nowhere else to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story starts with a long, violent prologue about a character named Will. While Davey is looking to understand how she ended up in the care of the cult, she doesn’t learn much about her biological family except through a tale told by the Reverend - the cult leader. It is well established by Vigna through Davey that the the cult leader does not tell the truth, though, so even if the prologue and his story might describe the same character and similar events, the reader can’t believe what the Reverend tells Davey. The story is gruesome, disturbing to read, and describes the life of a young boy who learns how to prostitute himself for money and the revenge he then seeks from his father. There are parallels that suggest that this boy grew up to be Davey’s father, but this is never confirmed. After the story is told, Davey meets the same character from the prologue, Will, and for some reason believes that he is her father although she’s got no reason for thinking this. The character Will dies shortly after being re-introduced.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a great deal of build-up to the reverand’s story, but everything that happens after feels misplaced. Neither Davey nor the reader find out who his story is about, nor how much is true. 100 pages in, there is an established cast of characters with confused relationships. Vigna has a habit of generating a great tension and then immediately and unceremoniously killing off the relevant characters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the story that this book tells is narratively interesting, Davey actually doesn’t change much at all for the remainder of the book. She starts out as a reluctant bystander to her carer’s crimes. She remains as such until the end. The woman who raises her, Bulah, starts off an accomplice to the reverand and remains so until the end. The other support characters who meet various fates do not go through great metamorphosis either. Even a prostitute, Laura Bell, who starts a tentatively hopeful family with an RCMP officer midway through the book, is once again a childless prostitute 26 years later when Davey encounters her in the epilogue. Maybe that is part of the point that Vigna is trying to get across - nothing and nobody really changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other reviewers seem to think that the major themes of this book have to do with confronting religion and wrestling with questions of fate and self-determination. I am of two minds on this - on one hand, this book can be read as being about the strength of religious influcence over group behaviour. On the other hand, it repeatedly emphasizes the a-religiosity and amorality of the roaming group of reverend’s followers, and Davey and a few others are seen to consistently reject his influence. As a character who starts off being a reluctant accomplice, her eventual splintering from the group is not surprising or undexpected. She is there because she is 14 years old. The reasons for her developing her opposition to the leader are never mentioned or explored. The only arguments of fate are ones that come from the reverand, who is from the beginning established to be manipulative and unreliable. Of course Davey escapes the first chance she gets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This book might have made more of an impact on someone who is more familiar with religion. Sometimes when reading fiction with religious undertones, I feel that there might be some hidden meaning that I’m missing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, the story of a group of roaming pillagers surviving in frontier Canada left me feeling haunted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Review&lt;/strong&gt;: 4/5 stars&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I didn’t expect to like this book. Actually, I had to force myself to start reading it after renewing it from the library a week late. Once I got started, though, I couldn’t put it down. This review contains many spoilers.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Book Review: The Quick Fix by Jesse Singal</title><link href="/2022/02/01/QuickFix.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Book Review: The Quick Fix by Jesse Singal" /><published>2022-02-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-02-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/2022/02/01/QuickFix</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2022/02/01/QuickFix.html">&lt;p&gt;Coming in from just having finished the slightly-more-dense &lt;em&gt;Turnaway Study&lt;/em&gt; (Foster), I expected to be reading a long-form review of the state of academic research and communication. Instead, I found this book refreshingly free-flowing and easy to read. It unexpectedly felt like I was having a casual conversation with the author rather than sitting down and putting in real mental effort into examining my worldview. However, despite some nods to the replicability crisis and the challenges of scientific communication in the introductory chapter, I found it to be relatively light on new information and opinions of potential solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I expected that this book about “fad” social science ideas which become bad policy. To his credit, Singal spends a great deal of this book writing about how movements based  on pleasant stories gain momentum, and how they succeed when researchers don’t have the right political or economic incentives to discredit them. He also spends time discussing the challenges of decision making for policy-makers, who often have incomplete information and therefore can’t discriminate between substantive and “fad” research. However, the chapters are very disjoint - Singal tells more or less the same story each chapter, and leaves the the broader takeaway open to interpretation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a book whose thesis criticizes the short, fast, TED-friendly style of glossing over important information, it’s ironic that in places it still does this itself. Singal spend pages of the book praising the careful methodologies of academics he will then later critique in some minor way, before admitting that he doesn’t fully understand some larger part of his target’s research. Singal’s message seems to be to approach extrapolating from limited experimental results with caution, and yet he himself appears to do so in the case of scrutinizing Kahneman, Thaler, and friends. I guess this is part of the paradox of the non-scientist scientific communicator and part of the problem that I hoped that this book would address.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, this book was fun to read. I experienced it as a series of disjoint case-studies in how innocent misinterpretation and over-extrapolation of results can and has ended up having dramatic influence over public policy (and therefore the lives of real people). I only wish Singal was not afraid to express his own opinions. Setting assize the topic of scientific communication, Singal spends a lot of his exposition criticizing not only the the marketing/commercialization of psychological research, but the fact of it’s application to policy at all. In Singal’s view, even if scientific communication was perfect and nobody ever sought to make a quick buck by overstating the effects of (say) power posing, applying results from experimental psychology to public policy would still result in ineffective policy interventions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Singal seems to imply that extrapolating from (individual-based) psychological studies doesn’t address institutional problems, and we need to instead take a more sociological approach. This is the common progressive critique - we can’t understand individual behavior divorced from the institutions in which it’s situated. It is obviously more difficult to sell the idea of power-posing or grit development or implicit association tests to someone who believes that poor outcomes for lower classes are the results of multi-causal institutional, rather than individual, failures. This leaves open the question, then - if individual psychological interventions are ineffective (and prone to over-simplification), then exactly which institutional interventions does Singal propose as alternatives?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know that Singal believes that effective institutional interventions come in the form of wealth redistribution and means-tested social programs, but these interventions aren’t discussed at length in this book. I would have enjoyed seeing a comparison between the outcomes and cost-efficacy of such (more sociological) interventions, compared to the costs of the failed (more individualistic or psychological) cases discussed in the book. My impression is that both approaches are similarly ineffective and would suffer from similar over-simplification and marketing issued brought up by Singal. I’m not sure which type of intervention is more costly. It would have been interesting if &lt;em&gt;Quick Fix&lt;/em&gt; addressed these questions explicitly. Instead, it avoids proposing effective sociological interventions altogether, opting instead only to gesture to systemic change as the answer to the enumerated failures of individualized intervention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;To summarize&lt;/strong&gt;: This book is series of case studies on failed policy interventions. They fail because they are attempts to apply results from psychology, which suffers from 
1) Being prone to exaggeration, misleading commercialization efforts, and difficulties in replication
2) Producing individualistic interventions for systemic problems&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Singal suggests that systemic interventions would be more effective but does not expand upon this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Review&lt;/strong&gt;: Very easy to read, 3/5 stars (+ for ease and entertainment, - for handwavy vagueness)&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Coming in from just having finished the slightly-more-dense Turnaway Study (Foster), I expected to be reading a long-form review of the state of academic research and communication. Instead, I found this book refreshingly free-flowing and easy to read. It unexpectedly felt like I was having a casual conversation with the author rather than sitting down and putting in real mental effort into examining my worldview. However, despite some nods to the replicability crisis and the challenges of scientific communication in the introductory chapter, I found it to be relatively light on new information and opinions of potential solutions.</summary></entry></feed>